Hello and welcome back to
another video with its Dr.
Dan.
And today we're going to be learning
about exceptions to the octet rule.
So we're gonna be explaining this today
with Lewis structures and being showing
when the octet rule breaks and fails.
So one thing that we were told in the
very beginning of chemistry is that all
elements follow the octet rule, meaning
that they always want to have eight
valence electrons around their outermost.
The thing about that is when they
do this, they want to bond with
things through ionic covalent bonds.
But the thing about it is it doesn't
always work the way it should.
There are exceptions to this rule
or violations of the rule, meaning
there's other things that are possible.
Sometimes you might see that they
don't always quite follow it.
So when does this happen?
What are the different types?
Well, there's three times that you
will generally see this happen.
The first one we're gonna talk
about is the in incomplete packets,
meaning there's just no more valence
electrons to make any more bonds.
We just can't do it.
And the thing is, those elements are
perfectly happy the way they are.
They don't need to have eight.
They are okay with the way they are.
Uh, sometimes you might have an
odd number of valence electrons.
Meaning that also can't quite get there.
And usually these are some of the
most reactive molecules possible that
are going to try to find something
else to bond to make that happen.
So we're gonna show
when are those possible.
Now, that's probably the
rarest instance for, especially
for introductory chemistry.
It's a little bit more common to see it in
general chemistry or maybe even organic.
But it's very, very rare that
professors and teachers give them to.
So three is the expanded octet, which
is when you have too many valence
electrons and essentially as a result
you can make many different bonds or
you can have like, uh, these very unique
molecular shapes that are being formed.
This is the most common one that's seen
in general chemistry that's given as
examples, especially when you're a val
shell electron pair, repulsion theory
or VSEPR to be able to pick out shapes.
All right, so let's take a look at these.
We're gonna go through different examples.
I'll try to explain them the best that
I can, and, uh, thank you so much for
stopping by and let's take a look at them.
All right, the first
example is incomplete octet.
So this is when we have
to, you balance electrons.
So when does this happen?
So this is typically on when we're in the
very early parts of the periodic table.
So for example, boron, which if you
look at that on your periodic table,
it's on the third column of your main
group elements, meaning that it only
has three valence electrons around it.
So being that this is a non-metal,
it's gonna have a tendency to want
to bond via covalent interactions.
So if that's to happen, let's say
I have boron around some hydrogens.
So hydrogen, we're gonna
put one on each side.
We're gonna put the one
valence electron for hydrogen.
And when we connect all these bonds,
you might kind of see that there's
a little bit of a problem here.
So if I count all of the dots
around the boron at the moment,
so we only have 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6.
Individual dots around boron,
meaning that we don't have eight.
And you know what?
That's okay.
That's perfectly fine to not having,
ideally you always want to have
an octet if you can get there.
But in this situation, you don't have one.
But this is where it's deficient,
doesn't always have the opportunity.
Um, another example of this would be,
let's say if I had boron with fluorines.
And now you might be thinking
like, oh, can fluorine give
some of its extra electrons?
Remember, fluorine is really greedy.
It doesn't want to give any of 'em away.
So, and also fluorine has a tendency
to only want to make one bond.
So if I were to put all the lone pairs
for a fluorine around it, you could
see it only has room for one bond.
That's only gonna make one in this case.
Alright, so once we connect all the.
Our bonds here and write them all in.
So drawing all of our dots.
Okay, we'll connect these with a little
yellow line to show our bonds click.
So, and once again you can see
that it only has six dots around.
We're on again line and all
of the fluorines are happy.
They have all of their valence electrons,
so it's perfectly okay the way it is.
There's sometimes that is.
Another example, sometimes like beryllium
can make the has deficient octets.
Uh, one of the most actually common
ones is thinking about the duet
rule, which is when I refer to how
many valence electrons, hydrogen
and helium have, so technically
they don't have an octet, right?
They can only have a total
of two valence electrons.
So if we're to look at two
hydrogens and we were to connect
them with a single line, well.
Essentially each hydrogen only
has two valence electrons around
each of its orbitals as it's
bonding with another species.
So, and it's fine with that.
It's has a complete level.
And the big reason is think
about the one S orbital, right?
We're thinking about how we
draw our orbital diagrams.
Well, if each one of them has essentially.
One s from each side
trying to bond together.
Right.
And we were trying to show that
when they do bond together, they
would, they would each give a
single electron from each side.
Just like so.
So they'll each add their own when they
are bonding at a, at a lower level.
Okay.
So that's something that's a
little bit farther along, but
they will share each share one.
Let's take a look at our
next sample of what else?
Break the octet roll.
Alright, so when else can the
octet roll potentially break?
Uh, let's look at this one.
It's when we have an odd
number of valence electrons.
So when you are writing a Lewis structure,
one of the first steps you should
do is count your valence electrons.
So here, if I, if I'm gonna
follow that right, nitrogen
has five valence electrons.
Oxygen has six valence electrons.
If you find yourself that
this, that you're wondering
where those numbers come from.
You're counting your columns of
the main group elements, the two
towers on the periodic table.
Um, one of those things is if you are
trying to watch us, don't understand
it, make sure you do understand
those valence electrons or used
all the time with Lewis structures.
So.
When we add these two together,
we have a total of 11 electrons.
'cause we want to show what
the structure is for nitrogen
Oxide, which is a greenhouse gas.
It's one of the most
reactive greenhouse gases.
So what we're gonna do here is
we're gonna draw each of those dots
around each of the respective atoms.
We have five around nitrogen, and
then we have six around oxygen.
Okay.
So when I do that, what we're
going to first do is we're gonna
connect with just a single bond.
And we notice neither of
them are currently happy.
Oxygen has a total of seven
dots at the moment, right?
So if I kind of count these, we
have 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, and seven.
It needs one more.
So what we're gonna do is
we're gonna make a double bond.
So let's.
And as a result, we'll have an eighth
electron here, and then we will
write our little double bond like so.
But the problem here right now is if you
kinda look, is nitrogen currently happy?
And the short answer is kind of not right.
You see as 1, 2, 3, 4, 5,
6, 7, something is wrong.
It's missing.
And that, where can it grab it from?
It can't just steal one from oxygen.
'cause oxygen is perfectly fine.
It doesn't want to all
of a sudden give one up.
So this is where formal charge is
something that will be a factor here.
So we could calculate it.
Is does this structure make
sense the way we have it?
Well, let's do it for oxygen.
Well, it has six balanced electrons.
It has four lone pairs.
And it's currently making two bonds,
so that has a zero, so that's fine.
Now what about nitrogen on the other side?
Well, nitrogen has five valence electrons.
It has right now three lone
pair electrons, and then it
has making two bonds as well.
So it, it also has a zero formal
charge on the left hand side.
So charge wise, it's actually.
Actually what it thinks it should be.
So what does that mean
about this molecule?
So NO is what we refer to as a
free radical, meaning like your
radical, it's like rock on.
It's like kind of, it's like, oh.
So what these are is, uh, when it comes
to chemistry is that there's very few
molecules that exist that are like this.
One of the things I said earlier
is that this is a greenhouse gas,
meaning that these are pollutants
in our atmosphere that are very,
very harmful to our atmosphere.
So this one is essentially when they
have, very few of these are stable.
When they have an on-the-ground
response, most of them are
extremely highly reactive.
The second they come in contact
with something, they're gonna react.
This is one of them.
So usually they are very rare to see
them in a general chemistry course,
maybe even organic chemistry as well.
So very rarely does an instructor assign
you one of, but if you do have one,
keep in mind they react right away.
So if an N no came in contact with
something, they would immediately try
to take an electron from that thing and
react because nitrogen wants the offset.
So it's going to try to
find that extra electron.
Okay, so that is another example.
Let's take a look at the last one.
The last type of octet rule violation
that you will see is when there's
an expanded octet, meaning that
there's too many valence electrons.
So from right here, what I'm showing
you is this is the most common form that
you see in a general chemistry course,
and it has to do with exactly where are
these elements on the periodic table.
So let's talk about why.
So on the left I have PCl5,
which is a real molecule.
You might get PCl5 on an exam
and you're like, brawl it.
What is the structure of it?
This thing is real.
It exists.
On the right hand side.
I have NCl5, which is wrong.
Does not, it is not possible.
You can't actually have it.
So why can I have one and not the other?
Both of them have five valence
electrons for their central atom.
Phosphorus has five.
So does nitrogen.
Why is one possible and not the other?
And just to kind of see that, right,
they are both in the exact same
position on the periodic table.
Right?
So that, that tells you is that
in thinking of those different
trends, is that if I were
to kind of label these guys.
Is they both have the same number
of valence electrons, right?
We got 4, 5, 6, 7, 8 valence electrons.
So they have five.
So what's the difference between one?
Well, one of them is on the second
level, one's on the third level.
So if you kind of remember where,
remember all of our rows here on the
periodic table, so we got 1, 2, 3, or
the different periods that we have.
This is the difference.
So it has to do with the orbitals of
where they are on the periodic table.
Nitrogen, if you can kind of remember,
has, has one s, two s, two P.
and then with phosphorus
it goes down to three P.
So I have here the orbital diagrams.
The thing is, that's a what's
available and if you remember
from electron configuration
is what is your first D level?
So here, notice how the D level.
Is 3D.
This is four D, and this was the
third row where phosphorus is.
So that's important.
So what that tells you is that on the
third level, the D electron orbitals,
they're there, but they're vacant.
It's like having an entirely empty
house that's been fully refurbished,
fully remodeled, ready to be moved
in, and they're like, you can
move in for free if you'd like.
And you're gonna take it, right?
Essentially you have that ability there.
So what's gonna happen is being that
that 3D orbital is available, it
allows it to be able to expand it's
octet and to bond with more things.
So now the whole idea here is
with that, that availability.
There's only so many bonds that
are realistically possible.
So it's kind of the way to look at
it is, let's say if I take the that
three s electron and I move it over
here to the far right to the D,
notice how we have five empty five
spots available for bonding, right?
There's needs one more electron, each of
these different orbitals that are here.
So I can kind of add in all of these
blue electrons just to illustrate,
Hey, we could have an extra one.
So five bonds are possible
as a result, okay?
And that's the most important thing.
So what that means is that the third
row of the periodic table is important.
So if you are, if you're at the
third row or below, they can expand
their octet and bond based on how
many valence electrons they have.
The phosphorus has five valence electrons,
meaning it can make five bonds if you
think of sulfur, which is next to it.
Heck can do the same thing.
It can bond to six different things.
Um, heck, even iodine or bromine or
chlorine, they can bond to up to seven
things if they were to choose to expand.
They're off that, it's a little funny.
Um, even noble gases are actually possible
for them to expand their octet and bond.
Oh.
Um, so this is generally,
when does this occur?
Does it happen all the time?
And the answer is no.
It only occurs when you have a
very electronegative element like
fluorine, chlorine, or bromine.
And there's a lot of them that are
trying to find their extra electron
any way they can and they'll
try to sneak their way or bond.
Okay.
So that's what we're going to be seeing.
So we're gonna do an example of that next
so that we can illustrate that so you
know how to across the paper problem.
Okay.
So the, let's go through an example of
how to draw Lewis structure for SF six.
So when we're going through this,
we need to make sure we're keeping
track of every single element.
The first thing we're gonna do is we're
gonna count our valence electrons.
So sulfur that's gonna have six valence
electrons on each of, for the one sulfur.
And then fluorine is going to have seven
valence electrons on each fluorine.
So the next thing we're gonna do is
we're gonna assign a central atom.
Now what we're going to assign this off
of is one, what can make the most bonds?
Sulfur is one of our elements that's
on the third row of the Pyrrhic table.
So sulfur can actually make a total
of six bonds that's around it.
So we're gonna draw six dots
around it, and it's gonna bond to
the six fluorines that are here.
So now the third step is we're going
to draw our fluorine and connect
each one of these around our sulfur.
So let's kind of draw all of them around.
Okay, so really fast drew
that really quickly for us.
That way it saves a little bit of time.
So one thing you notice, I assigned all
the valence electrons for each element.
Here we have six yellow dots for sulfur,
seven green dots for each fluorine.
Now what we're gonna do is we're gonna
connect them all with a single bond.
So just like, so we see
that they're all connected.
Now the thing is, so just to double
check, is you, we added our octet on
each of the outer elements, so that
was our lone pairs, and then we assign
any remaining electrons to the middle.
So the reason why that last step
is important is let's say if you
don't quite have enough outer
atoms to fill, it's expanded octet.
Then you shove those extra electrons
on the middle one because they
can handle it with the expanded.
So what you can see here is this
is the structure for SF-Six.
So this is an octahedral structure.
So that's the shape of it.
It actually has the shape,
kinda like eight-sided die in
one way to kind of look at it.
Um, so it looks like two pyramids
sort of inverted with one another.
So this is the Lewis structure of it.
So just to kind of show kind
of that, that shape here.
So if I were to kind of try
to draw that the best I can.
So like, so we would put a
little line to each flooring.
So this is with Vesper structures, and
then you can kind of actually like see how
the shape of it, so it looks like this.
And back to the bottom like so,
and all these other, other ones
which connect to the bottom too.
It's gonna be an octahedral, um,
which is one way to illustrate shapes.
Okay, so let's take a
look at our last example.
Alright.
Draw the Lewis structure
for ICL four negative.
All right, so this one's a little bit
tougher because it involves formal charge
and making sure that we have the right
bonds so iodine can bond to chlorine.
But the thing about iodine is,
remember it has seven valence
electrons, so does chlorine.
So iodine is capable of making
seven bonds, but we only
have four chlorines here.
So it's gonna not quite match up.
So let, it's gonna revolve that
last step, which is step five.
So first thing is raise.
Write down those valence electrons
so we can kind of keep track.
So we should have seven valence
electrons for iodine at the minimum.
And then for chlorine, we should have
seven valence electrons for each of those.
Now we have one extra electron, the
negative charge that's up at the very top.
So we'll just put one electron, we'll put
that in purple just so we forget about it.
Now, the first thing we're gonna
do is we're going to assign
what is the central atom here.
So our central atom is going to be
iodine 'cause it's people, it's on
below the third, third row, or below.
So this thing is gonna be people
of multiple different octets.
So what we'll do is we're going to draw.
Essentially room for the four
chlorines we're gonna have 1, 2, 3, 4.
And then what we're going to
be doing is putting in the
remainder of the seven electrons.
So we'll put that on the sides.
Now we're gonna put in our Chlorines,
and what I'm gonna quickly do is just
fast forward, so we put the seven
valence electrons around each Chlorine.
Okay, so now that we did that, we put
in all of our, our different electrons.
Now the next step is, so that's
completing your octets on the outer atoms.
And then what we're going to do is
then connect to these with a single
bond, just to illustrate that.
Okay, we are making bonds, so we got
one here, one here, one here, and here.
So hover on the other one.
So this is going to be complete Octets.
On all of the chlorine
said they're all happy.
Now we have essentially a problem though.
As you can see, there's one lone
electron on iodine, but don't worry,
we do have essentially our extra
electron, so all extra electrons they
get assigned to the central atom.
So we're gonna be putting
that right here like this.
So generally when we have lone pairs that
are on these expanded octets, usually
we'll kind of push 'em out a little bit
like this, and then it's very common
to draw a line to illustrate, Hey,
they're here, but they're pushed out.
So that way you can illustrate
the structure a little bit
better, um, just like this.
Um, now as a result, we can see those
lone pairs are, are above and below.
And then we have everything else
on here so we can double check
our formal charge for ourselves.
So, chlorine right has
seven valence electrons.
It has, uh, six lone
pairs and then one bond.
So that's completely happy.
Now let's take a look at iodine.
So iodine also has
seven valence electrons.
Right now it has four lone pair
electrons and it's making four bonds.
So it has negative one charge.
Which is exactly what we want
because it was I cl or minus, right?
Is what we started with.
So that was the beginning of our molecule.
So whenever we have an ionic species like
this, what we need to do for ourselves
is put it in brackets, illustrate, Hey,
there is this negative charge on molecule.
Okay?
That one minus charge, uh, that we.
It's like, so, okay, so this is how
the expanded octet rule can work.
These are rarer examples, but
typically it's whenever you have
these very low, non metals is
really the what you're looking for.
So just keep in mind, row three
or below, they are the most
common ones you're gonna see.
Um, the other ones is usually
when you have four on.
That one's a little bit
easier with when it's less.
Okay, so these three different
types of octet rule violations.
I hope this video helped you and
thank you so much for watching.
Bye now.